the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right we should just have a
listening music with daniel party
i think that would be quite fun um
welcome to the store everyone um
the digital porch third edition uh
so i imagine most people are aware of
the the format
uh this is sort of an open session so
unlike the other sense maker
in resident series uh there's no
prepared topic
or powerpoint or anything like that
we're just going to sit on the digital
porch and ask
daniel schmuckenberger who's the sounds
maker in residence for
for this day and this month um questions
uh and dana and i decided i mentioned
this in my mailing list uh
our mailing newsletter last night that
we're gonna just
uh have the tractor the broad attractor
of personal development
and personal practice during the
metacrisis or the transition between
game a game b
and this crazy time that that we're in
um
so we're going to stay away from more
abstract uh
things like the war on sense making or
system building and stuff like that
so that being said some of you sent not
that many people actually sent the
questions in
the survey but i might pick on you if
you you um or choose you i should say if
you
asked a question but feel free to drop
your questions in the chat
now um maybe have a question or q before
it if you don't want to be on youtube
just say read on
your behalf and i will do so um
that being said i will allow everyone to
unmute himself
daniel how's it going my friend
good good to see you peter i appreciated
your last
article that you shared right before
this on
reality tunnel switching right anything
um
come alive for you when you read it
how to navigate the interface of many
very different reality tunnels like
you were discussing a kind of particular
christian approach to thinking about
hell and demons and uh saints and then
come back to something like
philosophy of science and logical
positivism and say what the [ __ ] do i
make of that
is a very interesting and true tricky
topic
i don't know if that's the direction
we'll go down at all but it's an
it was valuable to at least have you
acknowledge
that gaining the first person experience
of
a way of experiencing reality is
possible without being obligatedly bound
to it forever
and then you can step out of it and do
something with it
so since i got first question rights i
will take us down there
um and some people did ask questions
related to
kind of like evil um so
i'll read a portion of the question um
is it necessary for us all together to
confront evil on a cultural level
i don't mean just the evil within
ourselves but also collectively
acknowledge
the shadow of psychopathy within the
collective conscious
um and i'm curious about this as i've
been writing about kind of like demonic
possessions and stuff like that
um and i am curious about what your
thoughts
are on what evil is as a phenomenon or a
construct do you think it exists it
doesn't exist and if you do think it
exists
or something like it exists how should
we personally and collectively respond
to it
i'm very curious to start that one with
a sampling from people here of how they
hold the concept
and reality of evil
how would you like them uh to indicate
that on the chats
or talk
uh anybody wants to maybe say something
just
kind of indicate in the chats uh i think
we should avoid popcorn style for this
one
um someone said that [ __ ] exists
uh tyson flows if you can unmute
yourself
sure thanks when i first thing that came
up for me was
um like something that something is in
like an entity an energy a person
that wished to
take advantage of me or like
my insecurities or weaknesses or
something to
um like create suffering in a way that
would
further its own interests and agenda um
yeah and and then the visual that came
with it was like energies i've
experienced specifically like in
dreams um
that it was like i was sleeping and i
was in my bed and i was like in this
like
totally like vulnerable state and like
some um
uh and i encountered this entity in a
dream
and it's like oh you're coming after me
like while i'm sleeping and i was like
that was kind of felt like an
encounter with something that was like
the closest thing to evil maybe i've
experienced
yeah peter can i uh pop in because i'm
the one that asked the question
sure um where i was coming from was
looking at how we as individuals talk to
each other and encourage each other
to do shadow work but it
there's a part of me that feels like
despite our best intentions and if we
all do our shadow work they're still
going to be
malevolent people and and to like
institutionalized uh
uh systemic psychopathy that will always
take advantage so that
basically it's like a feeling that
there's not much we can do
uh that's really gonna have any impact
on
that force
i get that sense
maybe since it was your question i'll
i'll uh
say something
i by no means i'm an
expert in the odyssey i have friends
that are scholars that have spent their
whole kind of thinking career on the
nature of evil from lots of different
reality tunnels
so i'm just sharing some
rough senses that i have of it
as soon as we realized that humans
really got creative with torture
techniques
and tried to perfect the amount of
subjective suffering that other humans
can go through
we realize that there's something more
[ __ ] up than just kind of
uh effective utilitarian game theory
there's something more [ __ ] up going
on there in the
reality of not just psychopathy but
sadism right
the actual positive experience
associated with the negative experience
of another
then when we use a term like evil as
opposed to
um a term like say malevolence or sadism
it engenders a metaphysical
sense of is
are there demons or entities or a dark
side of the force or a devil or some
kind of like is there
a foundational ontology of evil um other
than just it being distortions in the
psyches and
bodies and brains of people
and you know there's more religious
versions of that like
a devil or polytheistic or animistic
kind of demons ideas or
hungry ghost realms or things and then
there's kind of more
new age science versions like
morphogenetic fields sheldrake's work
maybe there's
morphogenetic field of
certain kind of self-propagating
destructive tendencies
i'm not close to the idea that there is
some antic reality outside of our
belief or perception of it about those
things but i have no
good reason to believe there is
more i have pretty good reason that when
people believe there is it is usually
an easy place for those people to get
messed up
i have found some people who take
seriously the idea of
demons and devils and whatever and some
good comes of it but it's
very easy to go down directions that i
would consider net not positive from
that belief
which is different than saying from that
as a symbolic psychological process
i think it can be quite valuable if it's
held as a symbolic psychological process
so
you're on a heavy dose of mushrooms
doing a mushroom journey
and you see some demons coming after you
and it's possible see like even
the cognitive frame of how to hold that
if someone holds it as the mushrooms are
helping them see into the astral realms
and the demons are actually there and
they have to like
protect themselves from the demons in
that realm because there's some reality
to it
i have seen people become traumatized
from journeys
in that way because now they are scared
of what's happening in the astral realm
they're scared to go to sleep
they need protection with them things
like that
if you hold these are phenomena arising
in my experience arising in my mind and
my phenomenology
and that can't actually hurt me
something arising in my mind can't
actually hurt my
other part of my mind or my body the
fear of it maybe can
so i go towards it as opposed to go away
from him the same would be say in a
dream we talked about this some last
time
and you know i had this experience
when i first turned towards the demons
and they
were gonna come eat me and i'm like this
is a [ __ ]
dream this is a trip great eat me like i
can't actually
die here go ahead and so then the fear
dissolved
because it couldn't actually really hurt
me and i'm like please eat me and then
so it tried to become something scary or
some nasty like
cockroach monster that was going to eat
my eyes out and there was a moment of
fear and i'm like no go
go for it and so then that fear can
dissolve so then it became like a black
hole that was going to swell up the
universe and like go for it
and then it was like a devil that was
going to eat my soul and like go for it
and then
it all just turned into light right
there
because there was no more fear there was
nothing that was going to get me to
go into reaction with another part of
myself
in that way um
so that was relating to demons in a
symbolic
way that created psychological
integration of parts of self
i think that can be very helpful
in terms of
psychology of sadism what makes people
like the psychology of sociopathy is or
psychopathy is one thing how does
someone have their empathy decoupled
from other people
where someone else can be feeling
something they don't feel anything
but then how does someone get to the
place where it's flipped right where
they actually feel
positive emotional valence on somebody
else's negative emotional
state
i wrestled to understand this because i
couldn't really access that experience
very much in myself
and i still don't know that i understand
it
competently or fully but i have some
insights
some people who when they were young
suffered at the hands of other people a
lot
felt controlled felt like they were in
suffering and felt very alone in that
when they go on the other side and
induce someone else to be in that
in that state there's something like
connection that occurs
someone else's experience what they
experience i have witnessed that as
one of the phenomena
also where someone had a profound lack
of control and they felt a lot of
uncertainty and fear and insecurity and
the answer was gain control
sometimes people who are sadists really
actually will take joy in bringing other
people excitement and bringing them hope
and then
and bringing them sexual arousal and
then also crushing them
and then bringing them back because it's
not just in
anti-coupling that they're happy when
the other person is miserable it's that
they're happy when they get to
experience their own control
over reality and particularly the
subjective reality of somebody else
so those would both be examples of
evil as a result of a compensation
pattern for trauma
right the thing that we would call evil
or malevolence and people as a
particular kind of trauma response
that's mostly how i hold it on an
individual level and then collectively
there are whole cultures that are
basically auto poetic traumatizers
you know that are traumatizing people
systemically and then those which is
then
conditioning people to propagate those
traumas
and so then you start to say like okay
well if it is autopoetic there's almost
like a being to it right like let's say
we take capitalism
capitalism is this auto-poetic
self-propagating self-evolving thing
right self-evolving because it goes from
barter to some people wouldn't even call
that capitalism yet but the
owning of capital property um
from barter to currency to fiat currency
to fractional reserve fiat currency
to algorithmic high-speed trading on
fraction reserve fiat currency it's
like an ai it's evolving its algorithm
for how it does that right so you're
like okay
who did that well nobody did that take
the person who figured out algo trading
out of the world
in history and somebody else would have
and so you're like there is some
auto-poetic self-propagating thing
that's happening there
is there almost like a spirit of that
thing an entity of that thing that's why
i really love that article on slate star
codex meditations on molok
because you know he's describing the
autopoetic property of
arms races and then kind of describing
what the spirit of that thing
seems like
and it is really tricky when you get the
sense of like okay
those who seem to do the bidding of the
game of power
those who seem to do well at the game of
power get more power in the system and
in turn
keep modifying the system to be better
for people like them
those who oppose the game of power
including the worst evils and injustices
of it are also opposing the people who
are doing well at it so then those
people work to
get rid of the other people and so there
is the self-reinforcing dynamic
and you're like that's a very powerful
collective intelligence what the [ __ ] do
we do to keep that thing from just
running to zenith which is a paperclip
maximizer
and this is i mean i think it was
intuiting that
after the you know world war one and
then world war
ii that led to lord of the rings and
star wars as these great
modern mythos right of sauron and the
orcs or uh
the death star and the empire that were
like this kind of
seemingly undefeatable self-propagating
paperclip maximizer type thing
and how was it that a small
rebel alliance or fellowship of a ring
could actually do something about it
i think the energy of hopelessness that
you
mentioned
is something that one needs to feel and
not pretend that they don't feel
otherwise they'll kind of fragment
inside
but then recognize whoa that
hopelessness
is actually an expression of the depth
of desire for hope in me which is a
which is a result of the depth of love
and care in me
and let me reconnect to the love and
care and then reconnect to my sense of
agency my sense of agency is overwhelmed
so i care more than i feel like i can do
anything
so how do i come back to the care and
then how do i look to grow or increase
my agency in steps
rather than be able to say okay my
agency's here
here's this whole set of issues i can't
address all of them so i'm just
overwhelmed
someone needs to take a more
developmental approach to how to
increase their agency
uh with that because otherwise i think
one of the ways that
evil gets to self-propagate is by
causing overwhelm in those that would
oppose it
right or basically decreasing will or
agency except where it has sociopathic
or sadistic expressions
because typically anyone who has
sociopathic or sadistic orientation
towards power doesn't get overwhelmed
and lose power
right they keep seeking how do i hold
empowerment more
so of course
okay two more things i'll say about it
when we ask what is
choice i'm
the whole question about will and
determinism is
like foundational existential question
but if we were to define choice as being
anything that is worthy of calling
choice
then it's distinct from just causation
or summed up causation otherwise there's
no basis to call a choice
and then we say what is a good choice
the fundamental question of ethics
we can say to the degree there is a
reality of choice
a good choice furthers the field of
choice
it expands the phase space of the
possibilities to keep choosing
so choice is reifying itself
whereas a choice that debases the
possibility for future choice is kind of
self-terminating choice
so if i am if i'm making a choice that
decreases my own agency and sovereignty
we can say pretty straightforwardly
that's not a good choice it ends up
debasing the possibility for choice
if i make choices decrease the agency of
others that
and i am not decreasing the phase space
of choice for the whole
that's also then the next level of the
question a good choice increases the
face space of choice for the whole
which also means the possibility of
choices that would
suck so you don't ever get an
absolute law or binding on no choice
that sucks without
actually debasing choice itself
um maybe you guys will have forrest on
some time to speak about that
that's kind of the beginning of how he
talks about choice and then he defines
evil as that which does not further that
which shuts down the possibility to
further
the reality of experience and choice
i have a rabbi friend who describes evil
as always being the result of a
breakdown in intimacy
and that i can't hurt somebody
if i feel really connected to them and
if there is a sense of us
as part of the web of life if there's a
sense of intimacy with each other in the
world
evil can't really arise in that presence
so they're
basically disconnectedness a breakdown
in the authentic intimacy of reality
because
because there is authentic connectedness
becomes the niche in which evil can
arise
probably just opened up more questions
than answered but those are the first
thoughts that come to mind
all right and and um forrest landry is
coming to the stoa on
october 27th for those of you who are
interested um
what's it called so keith yeah keith you
had a follow-up question
um so i had two sort of follow-ups
it's good to see you again um and so
the first follow-up is uh it can you
speak to the way
cultures select for institutionalized
sociopathy
and then the second one is and i'm
thinking about that in terms of
the pushing to the margins of perception
that you might see in media where
certain things are highlighted and
certain things aren't in a way that
allows the culture to ignore things that
uh might stop it
or make it second guess itself um and
then the second one is
uh kind of related to that how do you
set up your personal empathy stack
like what emotionally valent content do
you bring into your life intentionally
um to kind of
relate to the world
the first topic i've talked about on a
lot of podcasts of how
um how arms races work
and the cultures that do the more uh
effectively game theoretic things get
selected so i won't say too much on that
i think one thing i'll say
is because you brought up media
specifically
one very easy way to do one of the
easiest ways
for a whole culture to buy into evil is
to believe that it's righteous
and all you have to do to commit an act
of evil and believe it's righteous is
believe the other to
to be evil
and so it's easy to take other subjects
who have subjective experience and put a
label on all of them together that makes
them an object and actually makes them
a nasty terrible object right they're
terrorists
they're racists they're whatever it is
and now i'm not actually relating
to a being with feelings i'm relating to
some bad entity that needs stopped or
hurt
now to the degree that i heard it i'm
actually doing a good thing
and so
there's there's this ted talk everybody
should
watch uh it's called something like on
being wrong
and um it's this lady who
wrote a book and did this whole analysis
on people's psychological experience of
being wrong
um and in the beginning she asked the
question
what does it feel like to be wrong and
people say well it feels
embarrassing and shameful and stupid and
she goes no no that's what it feels like
to find out you were wrong after the
fact
but you were wrong for a while first
what did it feel like before you found
out well it
usually felt like being right um because
you were usually pretty certain that you
you're right
and in the same way what does it feel
like to do evil well it usually feels
like righteousness
right that's the holy war um
so in the name of i'm sure my side is
right and i'm sure their site is wrong
even though i haven't spent real time
with them and can't empathize with them
and only have straw man versions of them
i feel right in attacking them because
i'm on the right side of history uh
so anything that otherizes in a way that
disconnects our empathy which breaks the
intimacy
ends up making evil easy to propagate
and be hidden
that's one thing i'd say
and on the second question
i can't empathize
at the speed that i can take in
information about the world digitally
they have different process rates
so if i'm with a person in front of me
who's telling me about their illness or
their loss of a family member or
whatever it is i
can feel and grieve with them and
there's more of a binding because of
scale
of the information they're sharing and
the emotional experience they're in
and i can kind of process it with them
where my
my empathy doesn't leave me so
overwhelmed that my only opportunity is
to shut down
but if i take in the war in armenian
azerbaijan for five seconds as i move to
the war on the india pakistan border as
i move to the
increasing chance of war in the south
pacific seas as i move into starvation
in africa as i move into what's
happening in the amazon and some new
whales that went extinct and
there's no way i can [ __ ] feel that
right and so it actually starts to
condition
relating to information about others
without feeling
it starts to make that a pattern right a
pattern of dissociation
it's not very healthy so there's a
partly i would say
just reconnecting at human scale for
enough percentage of the time is
actually important if i'm
if i'm focused on what's happening with
animal rights globally
i need a certain amount of time at the
local animal shelter
with real dogs right with like just
actually connecting
to be able to ground it and if i'm
moving through the news quickly i need
some times where i move
not quickly and i'm not just trying to
info process i'm trying to actually
connect
to the reality of it that's one thing
all right any follow-up questions keith
i guess uh if i had a follow-up um
i am kind of curious i definitely feel
daniel uh what you're talking about with
just the getting turned off emotionally
by you know like i think anyone who's
engaging with highly cognitive you know
trying to save the world kind of content
is going to run into that barrier
um
and then it's like okay i guess like my
initial
thought is like okay well maybe i'll
just try to get
figure out like where my agency is and
then emotionally
relate to the things that i actually
have agency over and then
but then there's this question of like
is that fundamentally limiting my like
i'm limiting my scope
and do i just like turn on world food
maps and see
everywhere that's starving and then like
try to reorient with this more objective
overview i i don't know what you do um
so i'm kind of curious how you break it
down yourself
um this is a very crude example but
it's not worthless let's say you have an
athletic goal that's very far from where
you're currently at
so for fun let's say
you want to binge press 500 pounds
there's actually no amount of trying to
bench press 500 pounds it will ever
let you get it you'll just hurt yourself
because you your muscles can't actually
develop in that direction without bench
pressing 180 pounds and then 200 and
then 220 and
so you can keep tuning into it you can
keep watching the person who can for
inspiration you can keep being aware
that it's a direction you're wanting to
trend
but then you also have to come back to
actually work at the edge of where your
current capacity is
if you want to grow your capacity
because if you just keep trying to bench
press the 500
you can do that for years and never
actually make any progress
there's a similar thing where most of
your time
having your study be associated with
things you can do stuff about so you
also get closed feedback loops on am i
getting this right is it working right
i get some empiricism actually helps you
understand it better and grow your
agency
well having some attention on the bigger
problems to know emma
of all the directions i could develop
what direction do i want to develop in
um but they're in the same way that you
want to have a relationship between the
cognitive knowledge and the feeling you
cognitive knowledge of the big picture
and the sense of what you can actually
do about it agentically and that there
is a growth in your agency that could
converge
towards the things that you're studying
and it doesn't mean you have to know all
the steps of how it converges you
actually have to let go
of knowing that but you have to have a
sense that your agency's actually
increasing from the nature of your
endeavors
okay um so many good questions
uh ryan you're up next
hey daniel thanks so much for being here
i've been really enjoying
your work thanks peter for having us
so yeah just curious how you personally
parse those things apart how you
personally
avoid limbic hijacking in the ecosystem
of media as it is today
i don't avoid it
uh i would be i would be lying if i said
i could avoid it it's like saying
that i could smell pizza and avoid
having a physiologic response
hunger response like i might choose not
to eat it but a response is gonna occur
right and because there is a those
those molecules in the air have a
real response and the same is true with
those bits on the screen
and so when i see the framing of
um whatever right
cops attack a bunch of protesters and i
see that thing
i'm like i feel a fired up thing
so then the question is how do i process
that
since i know that
it has an effect and since i know that
it's all bias
i don't let myself share the piece or
believe it or act on it
before i do the rest of my sense making
work
right so i
then go look to see okay is there
another side to this story that's
reporting a different way and it usually
limbically hijacks me the opposite oh
those cops came after these people
attacked them
um and whatever and i see like a nearly
opposite limbic hijack
and so i can't say we'll have no
bias i can say we'll try to take more
different biases
that are in dialectic so that i'm not
just controlled by some of them so
rather than say unbiased i'd say bias
corrected
um
so simply identifying
whenever there is a view whether it
comes down to what is true
or a value statement that is polarized i
want to make sure that i actually
understand and
have felt and could argue both sides of
it well
before i share anything or take a
position
sometimes it's not just two things in
dialectic sometimes there's
a few perspectives that are really
different and trending i call that the
narrative landscape so i want to
understand the narrative landscape
um once i can kind of put myself in the
position of how different people are
seeing and feeling this
then i can kind of not just empathize
with them but also get some parallax
beyond it
all right um let's go with harry harry
you had a question
hey daniel um i just want to say i
actually
love listening to all your stuff so this
is really cool uh
my question is actually what you kind of
finished on
last time which is something you're
interested in around
how do we create
systems where we can best see where
people at different developmental stages
can develop
at what rates so my question is is on
the topic of that
how do we take into account the
different stages and i'm using the
integral model here
as we map out heading into game b and do
you have any insight into creating a
methodology that takes
each stage whether it's the ethnocentric
ecocentric
or the global centric stages into
account to bring us collectively
into the ability to hold that globalized
empathy or perspective
i actually think historically i'm bad at
this
um have zach stein come on and talk
about it he knows this much better than
i do
uh
i find that i can do a decent job with
this one-on-one where i'm getting to
ask a lot of questions and really get a
sense of
how someone is modeling something and
how they're responding
but as far as the generalizations of
different one-on-one learners into a
group that we call a developmental level
and how to
appeal to that developmental level
differently than other ones
i don't think that's something that i
understand well or i'm great at
uh i think it's important
which is why i would encourage you
having zach on uh
i think i can if i'm not talking to a
single person where i'm getting to
calibrate
i think i err on the side of assuming
people can hold more complexity than
they actually can
pretty often and then sharing things
that are actually not that useful
uh so i usually rely on other people who
are better at that
to help make sure that's being rightly
translated
and zach is coming back to the stoa this
thursday is going to be a guest star
with greg henriquez and they're going to
have like meta system sex so maybe you
can sneak that question there
um all right i think uh
who said this one uh regarding proto-b's
didn't copy and paste your name
if you're going to mute yourself if you
know who you are
oh nathan that's you
you're going to mute yourself
okay i'll read on your behalf nathan uh
regarding proto-b's i've been studying
aspects of proto-b structures that can
help transfer over to game b
how can we prevent them from becoming a
cult-like structure us versus the
mentality
would being physically decentralized
grouping help prevent some of this
uprooting not necessary
so it's a hard it's a hard topic
um i don't know the answer
because we haven't had proto-b's that
are successful to
like i don't have enough empirical
background on that in general
if a community wants to prototype a way
of living that's very different than the
rest of the world
they usually want a certain degree of
autonomy from the world to build that
culture and not have dominant culture
keep pulling it back into other norms
and usually they're doing that because
they think that there is some way of
being
uh and behaving together
that is better than the current social
structure so then it's hard not to have
a sense
of separation and better than and maybe
even assessment of real
like if you assess that current
civilization is a self-terminating
paperclip maximizer and most of the
aspects of culture probably part of that
it's very easy to do that thing again
where you
convert the subjects in it to part of
that object
structure um and you know feel
dissonance or superiority or at least a
lack of connection
and so to say well the goal of having it
be able to include everyone
well that's not enough because the
crusades had the goal of christendom
being able to include everyone right
um but in a way that didn't really
include
the actual intelligence of others that
might be different it just included that
everybody should think
the superior [ __ ] that we think
it's almost like there is a certain kind
of faith
in collective intelligence that is
important
where i have a sense that other people
who think differently than me if we can
engage in good faith that i would trust
the quality of the output of that
dialectic more than i trust myself
because possibly they'll surface things
i'm not seeing right like there's a
this was almost like the the spirit of
democracy that was held almost
religiously that there's this idea
of a collective intelligence that is
trusted where someone is willing to
lean in and do difficult work and make
compromises and listen to [ __ ] that they
don't agree with
and the thought that it could act is
actually has
higher potential for good
insight and sense making than them or
their
subgroup that shares the same bias as
you know i lived in this uh i went to
this university undergrad
uh called maharishi university and it
was a really funny place that maybe the
most extreme town gown
division that i have witnessed anywhere
because
uh there was a college in the middle of
the corn fields of iowa in this little
town called parsons college been like an
old beautiful kind of victorian campus
and uh there was this kind of vedic
hindu teacher who wanted to bring
meditation over to the west and then
actually have it be the basis of a whole
educational system and they were looking
for
university and they got this good deal
on parsons college so you end up getting
this like
university of higher education largely
based on eastern thought in the middle
of the corn and pig fields of iowa
and so so you've got like a
you know basically an intersection
between physics consciousness studies
and a hindu temple
and then you know a bunch of farmers and
it was very easy
to feel a certain sense of like
the better understanding and eliteness
of the people in the university
environment
and see the corn farmers as some
simpletons but it was only easy to do
that if you didn't interact with them
deeply
but then you interact with them deeply
and you find out that they actually
spend a lot more time on the earth and
under the sky and connecting to the
plants
than the people who are in the
university do and that there's a certain
kind of connectedness to nature and
wisdom and maybe
reliability and integrity that they have
that
that the people in the other place
didn't didn't have the same way
and so i think if the proto-b is
connecting with people outside deeply
enough to actually stay connected to the
the humanness of them so it doesn't go
into
kind of um separatist
superiority that's one helpful thing
all right um man i don't know a question
to choose
david sweadlow uh if you can
find yourself yeah thanks um i'm curious
what you're learning
um from your entitlement inquiry on
facebook
um we had we had a glassbeat game last
week and it came up and there was a
really robust discussion but i'm curious
what you're taking from the
comments there or your thoughts on that
uh premature i just posted that i think
two days ago and
have only had a chance to read about
half the comments and not
really sit with and reflect on them i
was i was actually
positively surprised that there were a
lot of quite
insightful thoughtful things from
different perspectives being shared
it was actually a higher quality
collective intelligence input for a
facebook thread than i
have experienced on a lot of other
questions i put out there
and so i'm kind of curious as to why
that is why that question in particular
posted a question of what do you feel
entitled to and why
uh and so of course people got into the
semantics of what does entitlements mean
are we saying entitled by law because we
all agreed
in law or entitled by um a cultural set
of norms or entitled by universe in some
kind of
absolute sense or um
and it is entitled as a court of law
would support versus feel entitled
um and then there's a big difference
between i am entitled to this versus i
value this and would work hard to
protect it but don't assume
that it is just a given um i think
one of the things that a lot of people
surface it was valuable is
there are human rights that i really
appreciate there's rule of law that i
appreciate but if i
feel entitled to it and everybody feels
entitled to it nobody takes the
responsibility to maintain it then it
will break down
turn into you know tyranny so it's
actually
critical to value it and not feel
entitled to continue to do the work and
maintenance
um
and so saying i don't feel entitled
doesn't mean a kind of nihilism of that
there
that we don't want a society that does a
better job of rights it means
that we have to bind the responsibility
to do the work to ensure that thing
one of the things that i noticed is i
didn't ask the question
what does your behavior demonstrate that
you feel entitled to
in your day-to-day interactions that you
aren't admitting
like if you thought more about it
because a lot of people took it to the
macro level of what do i feel entitled
to by the state or by
the market or by law or you know by god
or something like that
but it's interesting how often we just
get pissed off at someone else because
they didn't do the dishes or whatever it
was or they didn't
you know tell me the thing or
acknowledge me or and it's very clear i
felt entitled to
like i i felt that they were supposed to
do that thing and i got disappointed and
upset when they didn't and so
it was very interesting to see how many
people said i don't feel entitled to
anything which means when they're
cognitively reflecting they acknowledge
that that is the like
formally true thing but then to take the
next step of
but where are all the places where that
actually is in your experience and what
do you do
about that differential so those
first few insights but i'm actually
looking forward to having some more time
with it
all right uh kelly you are up
hi uh can you hear me okay
so thanks uh first i want to thank you
daniel and contextualize this
through one of your past appearances
here where someone asked you about
something you connected with right
livelihood
and you basically propose that we can
think of livelihood outside of the
context
of income and what it is that is
mean what matters to us and then pursue
that
so that kind of like unlocked me to
think about what matters to me
and i found a thing that matters to me
and i've been beginning to work on it
for me that thing is homelessness and
i'm working on contextualizing it
i'm aware my work is like pointing out
what we here probably all know that it's
rooted
in these systemic issues systematic
issues like the game a world right so
all my work
in trying to conceptualize it i'm
getting stuck because i don't
i can't see the new vision the new story
of homelessness so my question for you
is what do we do when we know what
matters to us
and we understand why it matters and
like what the barriers are
but we're in need of frame breaking in
order to unlock
this the new problem space so to speak
if that makes sense
one thing i try to do is to see if
anyone has actually
figured key parts of it out that i'm
just not aware of
um i like to know where the boundary of
the best thought is because i
acknowledge that there's a lot of smart
people that have spent a lot of time
on a lot of these things and it might
not be like common knowledge but it's
knowledge um then if nobody has worked
on something
knowing that is really valuable and then
i say okay well what is the process for
to get other thoughtful people and kind
of work on this thing together and
figure it out
but uh as far as homelessness goes like
i think the
the first process that comes to mind for
me is i would
i would look at
examples of places that don't have
homelessness and
what they did right i would do a
positive deviant analysis
positive deviant on any problem is where
you have a distribution and you look for
who's doing best with that thing to
understand the mechanics in common of
that
i would look for any places that have
had relatively good homelessness
solutions
they had homelessness and now they have
much less or much less
you know consequential homelessness and
see what interventions have worked well
and then similarly what are the projects
that are in process that seem best
informed
uh so you know i know of a few on this
topic
mimi silbert and the delancey street
foundation did really good work
on um reform
of uh drug-addicted violent felons
um usually multi-generation drug
addicted violent felons so they were
born into gang families or whatever
and getting them to be able to hold a
job and hold a home and stay out of
prison so it was homelessness but
a deeper set of things and they
ended up figuring out some things that
worked really quite well and lastingly
um i have a friend named nelson del rio
that i think has one of the best
homelessness solutions that i'm aware of
that uses mostly market solutions
where he can make affordable places
where people pay rent that are is
actually rent that is going towards
ownership
and a co-op model that is goes along
with teaching
people financial literacy and job
literacy and those types of things so
the homeless people go from homeless to
having a place to be to eventually
gainfully employed homeowners and the
kind of responsibility of ownership that
comes
um and he put together a financial model
for a real estate play that makes that
possible i think that's probably one of
the most promising things
um there's obviously the like make tiny
homes and put them somewhere and put the
people in them and it's cheaper than
what it costs to keep putting them in
jail
and having them not on the street not in
jail is probably better but if it
doesn't offer some
like developmental direction where they
become more self-authoring
that's still pretty limited and uh
so the direction where people are not
just living on a handout or not just
renting but moving towards
uh a sense of something like ownership
um with as long as we're within a frame
like capitalism
uh is quite helpful
uh kelly looks like you have to follow
up if you want to jump in
well i so that's i really appreciate
everything you said
and it makes me reconsider if i was like
thinking too big
but maybe i want to press you and and
my thinking is that all of the things
you described
similar to like all the like silly sort
of toy ideas i thought of
are still kind of framed in
working which i guess we have to work
within the systems that exist so but
i'm more like curious and maybe it's
just an impossibility like
to how do you like i want to think of
like or like work with other people
to discover like a new vision or like
rediscover an old vision
like how do we like to me when i see
homeless people
i recognize that they are like trapped
in a space
and i feel a certain way towards them
that i know like other people don't feel
so i want to figure out a way where
people we don't have to try to do
anything
to make it so that like homeless isn't a
problem but so that people have a new
sense of what
you know what i don't know i might be
thinking too big and maybe i just need
to start
in a more practical way say again
you were starting to say that you you
want people to have a sense of
so oh i like i i think the like ideal
solution
is that people have a sense that
or maybe i'm just trying to reconnect
the dots but the thought i was going
with was
like if you have to create a program
to remediate homelessness then you're
not re-envisioning homelessness
you know if if homelessness if the way
that we envision
the thing like the this the contributors
to homelessness
were truly changed then you wouldn't
have to try
which i think so the point that you made
about looking where homelessness isn't a
problem i think that's actually a really
good idea i didn't think of but um
i don't know if that gives you anything
more to think about or if i'm again like
kind of pushing too hard
yeah so i mean if you want practical
examples
you look at place where places where
there isn't much homelessness or where
they've solved homelessness problems
and you see what they did because then
you know it actually works maybe that
maybe their situation doesn't work for
all other situations but
at least in some context works then you
need to make sure you understand the
context well enough
was it a country that has a big
sovereign wealth fund that was able to
afford it and other countries couldn't
or was it a small country that had a
very strong religious homogeneous
culture that had a sense of
you know charity like because if you try
to apply something
that was unique to a context outside of
that context you might be missing
something
but you can at least start to see some
things
there are other ways to reimagine
homelessness so you can
there are some future oriented projects
that don't assume capitalism
or don't assume you know private
property ownership of homes or something
like that
they'd have thought about re-envisioning
homelessness like the venus project
um jacques fresco of the venus project
was
actually very influential for me early
on um
and you know he's passed now but
uh the venus project continues and peter
joseph is extending
some of that work and so they
propose a kind of commons-based
cybernetic society in which most
property is not based on private
property ownership but generative access
and so you can look at something like
that from the point of view of like
reimagining at a whole global
level though of course there's a couple
questions you have to ask one is it's
never been
implemented and you have no idea if it's
actually going to work
and two you have to ask in order to get
it implemented and to have it work what
does it take
and one of you know peter thiel's
question of
you have an idea that you think is
better there's some people who really
don't like that idea what level of
violence do you need to employ to get
that
idea put in place and is it still a good
idea factoring the amount of violence it
takes to make happen factoring counter
pressures
which is kind of a classic libertarian
question
right which is since i'm not god or
king and get to just decree it be so
the kind of omniscient question of what
can't we all just get along what's the
best way that we could just make it all
happen well
okay there's a pretty big gap
from imagine right john clinton singing
imagine to how the [ __ ] do we build
anything here with all the people doing
the things
where with with
some people really wanting a zionist
israeli state and some people really
thinking that that's the great tragedy
and the world can't be okay until it's
gone and wanting a caliphate and
um some people really believing in
social darwinism and wanting the wealth
concentration and
you got to say okay so with this world
with these [ __ ] people
right and these dispositions how do we
move this thing forward so it's valuable
to imagine what it could be
but then the path there ends up being
where there's a lot of devils in the
details
that ends up being very kind of
meaningful so this is why i have much
more appreciation for the things like
what nelson del rio's doing
that are can actually take people out of
homelessness
and actually put them on a path towards
more self-authorship
in the current world effectively without
needing violence
and i'm like oh that's actually quite
meaningful is it
and and can it continue to advance
itself can it develop capacities that
can be reinvested to develop more
capacities
so that it eventually converges
as far as other things where you can
think about reimagining homelessness you
can go backwards
and look at indigenous cultures where
there's some sense okay nobody there was
homeless they were all kind of
communally cared for but then you can
then you have to ask why did that thing
stop
and is that commensurate with the ideas
of classical liberalism
um and kind of nation liberal nation
states
which it's obviously not and so then you
say well from
the nation-state liberalism capitalism
point of view where people
are wanting where there's a system
that's wanting to
at least in theory maximize individual
independence and sovereignty and not be
controlled by some top-down state that
we don't trust
or some top-down organization then
that also means people can [ __ ] their
lives up and what responsibility do they
have
for themselves and how do you solve the
free writer problem of if the
if some other group is then
obligated to wealth redistribute how are
they obligated is there some
physical violence that is going to force
them to put their capital there
so these are
these are tricky problems a lot of
people have thought about these things
maybe you will come up with some very
meaningful breakthroughs that nobody has
and i would say if you're willing to
dedicate some
real earnestness to it you probably can
and enough people have done
enough good thinking it's probably worth
understanding
both the success examples and the
problem space
pretty well
and then there's that saying the master
has failed more times than the
average person has tried
for you to make real innovation in the
space
will require not getting disheartened
when it's really when
almost all of your answers are wrong for
a long time
all right uh christian you just popped
in a question that's interesting if you
can unmute yourself
yeah sure daniel
my question is what are the aspects of
personal development and personal
practice that you've been thinking about
the most lately
um also where do you think
in terms of personal practice and
development
we need to pay generally speaking the
most attention to like where are we
lacking the most
and what's getting um looked past and
then
what are any like recent developments
you've seen
uh in these areas like maybe in terms of
new psycho technologies that are popping
up
that would be useful for people to
explore
thanks
i really like the bildung concept
that thomas bjorkman has been talking
about peter v
thomason good
because it transcends the
agency communion or individual and
collective divide which is how do i
develop myself
as an individual in service to bettering
not just my life as an individual but
the collective um
so it's personal development of
effective citizens not just effective
people
uh i think those ideas are very often
decoupled where there's personal
development for
like most people's vision boards when
they're doing personal development
is like a dope life for them um
and pretty individualistic and they're
doing good to the degree that that makes
them feel good and it's a dope life for
them
um or someone is willing to
work for the collective at great
sacrifice so they'll go be a soldier
or they'll be a frontline non-profit
activist worker whatever but they
are developing themselves to a limited
point
to start to use themselves and not
continuing to develop themselves to be
in greater and greater service
so the idea of an ongoing development of
self
to be ongoingly useful to all
other selves uh i think it's really
important that those two are bound
so that's one thing i would say and so i
i really like the
the build-on kind of model for that
and then with regard to specific
psychotechnologies
so let's let's kind of categorize them
you've got things like cbt
and the lefco method
and byron katie's the work and basically
cognitive models
where you're doing you're looking at
experiences that have you create a
generalized belief or meaning
structure and then working on seeing the
effect of that belief or meaning
structure overlaid on other environments
has it's not effective in working on
changing that belief or meaning
structure
and then you've got uh
emotional work like um
gestalt and catharsis work and
emotional release and primal screaming
and things that are around
where emotion was experienced and there
was kind of physiologic
sensation emotional sensation and it
didn't get to move how do we actually
allow it to
move through us and out
and then you've got somatic work like is
there a way that this is connected to my
body
of the kind of embodied cognition the
brain is not the only
part that has consciousness related to
it so you have
trigger point work and heller work and
somatic experiencing and all these
things that are working on connecting to
emotions in connection to the body and
moving them or unwinding there
then you have like sensory stuff like
where someone is triggered whenever they
hear a loud
sound because the gunshot sound that
happened in vietnam
or they're bothered by yellow because
that was the color of the
room that they were beaten when they
were a kid or whenever they see a man
that looks like a certain thing that
there were sensory
images that were pavlovian associated
with traumas
and they want to change those sensory
conditions that are the triggers and so
you'll see things like
nlp techniques that are designed to pull
up sensory images
and or some psychedelic assistant
psychotherapy
and change the pavlovian association
with those sensory images
i would say that those are not
fungible the those all do different
valuable things
and they don't do the same valuable
things
and so
i'm i'm as far as psycho technologies
i'm less interested in like here's a
favorite psychotechnology and more
saying
it's valuable to be aware of the
different spaces and levels in which
they act
and the partial value that they each
have and the synergies that can be there
between them
so that someone kind of pays attention
to working across those spaces
i had experience of going through a
particular psychotherapeutic process
and going through my whole childhood all
the events linearly
and having healing around all kinds of
things and then going through a
different psychotherapeutic process they
work from a totally different angle
going back to the things and having
totally different insights that related
to increased
freedom and happiness and capacity you
know many times
um and i think that's where things like
the integral model come in that are
saying how do we take multiple different
valuable things see which ones are best
for us at a given time
and how to not become a fundamentalist
to one
technique but to be able to see what
actually seems meaningful
and useful so i would say the binding of
the
development of the individual to their
dharma and the contribution to the whole
and the binding of the different parts
of self work to each other
uh are a couple things that come to mind
for me
so i have a follow-up question uh with
that
so christian who who just spoke he's
doing something at the store called
bespoke
psycho technology where he's you know he
shows his own psycho technology stack
and kind of
empowers us to figure out how to create
our own uh and and as you know we have a
wisdom gym
here at the stoa where we have
reoccurring events like collective
presencing
empathy circle we have a wim hof guy
comes in three three times a week
bioenergetics is coming um and
we're doing like these short research
type r d projects where
like margaret the lady who spoke last
week we did communitas club where we're
investigating all these different
intersubjective and conversational
modalities and if they work we can
import it in the wisdom gym
we're going to have something like a
psychotherapy cafe where we do the same
with all these modalities
a sovereignty society and the idea is to
have sort of like a
robust wisdom gym maybe like a metasanga
that has all these different kind of
practices and maybe wisdom trainers can
kind of guide people and all that
other than that i have no idea what i'm
doing but um given
all that that framework i just said do
you think there's any potential there
and how would
what would you uh say to guide that
process
a couple of thoughts that come up is uh
there's some kind of developmental work
that makes shifts that once they've
happened they can't be undone
right they're really kind of directional
shifts
and then there's other kind of work that
is really more like exercise like
you can be very buff and stop exercising
and lose it and it really requires
maintenance and it's valuable to know
which is which
um because one of the things that can
happen is someone takes a period where
they're doing a lot of study or a lot of
developmental work
they reach a certain level of clarity
and feeling of empowerment where they
start saying okay now i can go build
stuff in the world based on this
but it's some stuff that requires
maintenance they drop the maintenance
and they're like taking it for granted
and then lose the the foundation with
capacity
um so it's valuable to know
what kinds of things are like oh i've
i've had that insight
and now i can never see it the same way
again versus
um this is a kind of muscle that has to
be ongoingly
it might not take as much work to
maintain it just like muscles as it does
to develop them
and then what is an ongoing development
routine i think maintenance is super
unsexy for the most part
i think like new [ __ ] is has its own
novelty uh dopamine hit to it
and in general like
it's more fun to build a house and get
to see
there's a house and there wasn't a house
than it is to like wash the dishes
forever
and all i get to show for it is forever
that they're
it's the same as opposed to that it's
different in a finite period of time
um and yet the house is not very good if
i don't do the maintenance stuff right
um and so i think one of the things
that's super valuable is to actually
culture a very high value around the
maintenance
because otherwise there's a whole lot of
take two steps forward and then take two
steps back and
it's all very exciting and that net in
ten years you actually didn't change
your life very much
versus if i can make a small bit of
progress but maintain
it and this progress i made in my
relationships when i was putting a lot
of attention there
now when i go to put movement in my
business i don't lose the relationship
focus because i'm doing the maintenance
even if i'm only making a small bit of
progress in an area at a time but then
i'm maintaining the areas that i
developed over the course of a decade i
might have actually moved a lot
so i think actually creating a high
value around
the maintenance of things that are
meaningful and that require it
is very helpful
and then another thing when you're
talking about uh
you know a wisdom gem is
when i shared that there were processes
i went through
that were very powerful and then
later on different processes or
sometimes even the same process just
later with more emotional majority that
had whole other layers of insight
i think there's a benefit to settling
into
the personal growth happens forever
there is not
like uh i'm going to push real hard and
get there and then once i'm there then
i'll be able to do my work in the world
then i'll be able to have a relationship
or be fulfilled it may be
that there is a particular place i want
to get to before i move attention
to like just not be depressed all the
time or to feel like i can communicate
well enough to have a decent
relationship
but i'm still going to be working on my
own evolution as a person forever
in layers and so there's a certain kind
of settling into that
that is willing to
and takes delight in continuing to put
effort in
without the impatience of when do i get
there
that's uh that's helpful
yeah we'll keep the mind is uh like
similar to spiritual bypassing maybe
there's like spiritual distraction where
like oh i have to
you know level up before i actually like
engage in my dharma in the world
um you see that as a phenomenon
yeah i remember
i mean it was so important for me and it
sounds so immature and it was
but uh
it's usually hard to see ourselves as
really immature in the moment because
we're looking through the lens
that we have um in retrospect it's
usually quite easy
uh i remember
i had this very strong when i was young
monastic impulse
and a very strong
um romantic poetic lover impulse
and they were very torn
the monastic impulse was both in terms
of like depth of meditation and practice
and
dharma work that i wanted to do that i
thought would be so consuming that i
couldn't possibly be a good partner and
i didn't want to be a shitty partner
but i also had this sense that the
foundation of the meaningfulness of
everything is love and there's a way in
which that
expressed itself an intimate
relationship that was so meaningful one
to be honored
this was like a huge source of inner
conflict in my early
life
and so at one point i had to uh
say okay i'm gonna give the monastic
thing full rain so it stops pulling me
out of not being able to be in my
relationships fully
so ended a relationship with someone who
was really incredible who i really loved
i was maybe 20
and took a one-way plane ticket to peru
to go off in the
jungle by myself and however long it was
going to take to be with myself
and do the things that i needed to do
and it was really important that it was
a one-way plane ticket
and that i said goodbye to everybody and
that i didn't
bind it and one of the there were a lot
of very powerful things that happened it
was very good that i
gave myself that not everybody needs
that at all i
i did because i had a lot of heroes
that were monastic when i was young or
you know something like that
but one of the major things that i saw
that brought me out of it was
that life had really made this perfect
personal development ashram for me and i
was just rejecting it because i had this
idea that i was supposed to do this
monastic thing and i'm like
actually when i was in relationship and
when i was in work i was getting
confronted by my triggers all the
goddamn time which were my own lack of
wholeness which is exactly what i needed
to work on
but rather than embrace that as my
development i had some idea of no
no spiritual looks like this other thing
and i need to go do this and i'm like
actually it's kind of easier to not be
triggered out here and it's also kind of
meaningless and there's certain kinds of
growth that i just can't get out here
and there was a deeper embracing of
uh kind of
all of life as a developmental path
uh rather than being separate so
yeah yeah yeah i was gonna um like
mention like the monastery is your world
type thing or the world's your monastery
and then each thing is a forcing
function to
to improve and develop i i want to sneak
in another
question in regards to the um the wisdom
gym uh
margaret and i were kind of like we're
collecting all these different practices
and we're
thinking of having like multiple
taxonomies or meta systems to kind of
organize them
um and and for the psychology of
practice that might form
in the wisdom gym do you have
any you personally use or any recommend
maybe descriptive
like meta systems or frameworks maybe
like ken wilbur wilpers like growing up
showing up cleaning up um and ones that
might
like systems that might help negotiate
what practices to do
uh at any given time
yeah i think the
wake up grow up show up cleanup model is
a nice model
um
i found that this specific type of
methodology matters less than someone's
connection to the therapist if they're
working with someone
um if your therapist says they're doing
gestalt or cbt or jungian work they're
really just a person that has a lot of
experience
and if you feel like they have an
embodied wisdom around things you're
working on and you feel like they grok
you
then what happens there will be beyond
whatever the method
that they claim they primarily do is so
uh as far as working with somebody goes
i think the feeling of
right connection is pretty important
more important than
a model idea of appropriate method
and then one
person that you're working with might be
relevant for a while until whatever that
is completes and then something else is
you just have to be careful when you
feel a sense of completion
is it actually completion or is it now
we're getting to the stuff where they're
pushing on something i really don't want
to see
and so i'm trying to get rid of them um
so you know that's just the depth of
earnestness in our own inquiry
um and similar to that i would say
there's one can have a model of okay
well i did this lectical assessment on
myself and i'm in this level of
complexity of development therefore
these types of models are the most
appropriate
meditation or psychotherapeutic process
so i'll do it i'm not saying those
considerations are worthless but
paying attention to what your experience
and a different practice is and doing
the ones you feel called to is also
pretty important
um i think if you're doing a practice
and it doesn't
feel resonant it doesn't feel like
anything's moving
you can give it if if you've heard
really good things about it you can give
it good face
attempt for a long enough time to see if
it clicks but it
you're also going to get more movement
out of something that you do because you
feel resonance with it
so basically i'm saying i wouldn't try
to formalize it too much
right yeah that's been my intuition
as well and sometimes it's actually
critical
to pay attention to something that is
experientially meaningful that you don't
cognitively understand
and where it's actually critical to not
cognitively understand it
you're somebody does a session with you
with crystals or chakras and it's like
actually profound and you notice that
you're not triggered by [ __ ] anymore
you're like but i don't necessarily
believe in crystals
you don't
like it's easy to say okay well for
crystals to work it either means that
it's a placebo or it means that it's
some electromagnetic effect based on the
crystalline structure of the molecules
in the lattice
well maybe not maybe it's a whole other
set of [ __ ] that you're not that's in
your unknown unknown set that you can't
conceive of properly
so it's okay to say
i don't necessarily believe in a
specific proposition of how crystals
work but i believe in a meaningfulness
of my experience that i'm letting myself
have
and so i don't have to become across the
light of a specific way of describing it
that doesn't make sense to me but
because it doesn't make sense to me i
also
don't have to reject the experience
sometimes it's important to let yourself
have an experience that feels meaningful
and you'll understand it progressively
more later
i like that a lot someone joe's on the
chats uh you don't get to choose
what ends up working um
all right so let's uh sneak in one more
question before the hour
uh hannah you had a question
i do thank you thank you for teasing me
um so i would very much
like to start bringing some of the tools
that i'm learning here
to some of my other communities and
relationships
and so i'm wondering uh
what what skills can i work on
interpersonally
interpersonally to start
facilitating or moving towards
meaningful conversations between tribes
so something else are a meta thing i'll
comment here
is this whole format is just weird
this this format we're doing i
appreciate it i think
um i i hope that people feel that there
is some
uh value in it it was a experiment for
me and it was for
um peter
i didn't feel like saying yes to sends
maker in residence to speak on some
topic i've spoken a bunch of times
somewhere else
um but it felt like since this was live
and it was a community of engaged people
um and inter interested in the
intersection of personal
growth with meaningful topics in the
world a chance to like just talk about
what's alive
on the personal growth side would be
interesting but the like one-to-many
structure is strange because there's
plenty of people on the call who have
wisdom on these topics that i don't have
and yet we have an hour
here together whatever it is um
i'm glad that there are many other uh
people that are contributing to this
place and i i imagine
i hope that you guys have people like
diane hamilton and
zach and um maybe verveiki and other
people that have
worked with people for a long time have
a lot of depth of experience that are
part of an advisory council that is
ongoingly contributing
i imagine that's the case but normally
if i was having a conversation with
anybody here one on one
i wouldn't answer questions typically
like the question having you just asked
me the first thing i would do is ask you
back
what is your sense on that what are you
working on where do you find that you
have
limitations in that currently and yet
that doesn't scale to being able to talk
to when there's hundreds of people and
trying to say what about this question
might be relevant to everybody so
just even as a meta point
um a question straight to an answer is
usually not the best method of either
learning or healing
but the it's nate the nature of the
format
if you're interested in actually
facilitating i would say pay attention
to which
methods you're going deepest with and
getting the most benefit from
and actually see if they have programs
where you can learn how to be a
facilitator
many people learn at a certain point in
their life how to be a
therapist of a particular kind not
because it's their dharma to do therapy
forever but because
they're deepening their own knowledge
and practice of it
and oftentimes if there's a pattern
that's really deep for you and you
work with a lot of other people who have
it and seeing clearly and objectively
the way it shows up in them
you get deeper and deeper insights into
it um
so yeah you might actually decide to
take practitioner training
and then as far as bringing it to
different
communities and what skills you would
develop other than just the practitioner
ones
the ability to translate reality tunnels
or translate ontologies can be very
interesting
now it's just a kind of like cognitive
philosophic thing that is not
necessarily always relevant but if
you're wanting to bring some
experiential phenomenological thing to a
rationalist
community that maybe doesn't have a
doesn't even have antique
entities for those things right like um
then being able to translate it in a way
that can relate to something they do
have a relationship to
uh and then kind of on board just the
willingness to explore
um that can be very helpful and so this
is like the skills i would say are
twofold
one is the ability to say okay well what
is this kind of ontologic
worldview what is this one and how would
i translate them and that's kind of like
a communication
clarity process the other is an empathy
process of being able to see what are
the people here actually interested in
and what are they open to and how do i
connect there
i don't know if that answers at all what
you're
asking would like to
follow up hannah
i don't think it does answer it but i
think
you've stated why and some methods for
moving forwards
anyways and i am satisfied by that
fairness
and i believe that is uh the time here
right peter
yep uh we're gonna land the plane now uh
any any closing thoughts
uh for us daniel i'm also curious uh
maybe something you can mention later
but anything you're interested about
this community in particular
these sessions um that might inspire
some questions for us
for next time
yeah i think i'm particularly interested
in
the people who are called to reimagine
the future whether it's the future of
homelessness or agriculture
or economics or law or whatever it is or
all of them together you know game b
some kind of
new world the people who really care
about that and want to think about it
and work on it
and find community of other people who
do
and who recognize that not just their
cognitive learning but their development
in other ways is part of that because
they
they want to already become citizens of
that world right they want to notice the
the non-game b resonant things in
themselves
having been conditioned in this world
and work to like become inhabitants of
that world so they can sense it better
and help bring it about
um i think that's a
that's a necessary and particularly
beautiful intersection
and so what i was interested in here is
people who are considering the big
picture and considering some of the
difficulties of how do we transition
with multipolar traps and with whatever
and then what happens in me that
decreases my capacity to be effective
with that or that could increase my
capacity
the intersection of the like what do i
work on in myself
to increase my effectiveness in my
being of service to this larger thing
that we're all here on how do we address
the meta crisis
i think that is what i'm most interested
in with this community what i'm most
hopeful about
and specifically more questions in that
vein would be what i'd be interested in
doing addressing in our last
time speaking together great
so i'll probably send out a survey with
that frame and we'll get some
questions in for your last session uh so
daniel thanks so much
for coming to the stop once again we'll
see you next week
um i will make some closing
announcements uh but first let's
take in tyson because uh right after
this uh
we're going to stay on the same link and
there's going to be rap unbattles
that's going to be led by tyson flows so
tyson
if you can kind of unmute yourself and
plug that sure thank you yes in this
same room we are going to be engaging in
the third
version of rap unbattles which is a new
experiment here at the stoa where we
repurpose
freestyle rap and the concept of rap
battling
but instead of trying to like make our
point prove ourselves right
win over the other person we take
freestyle rap and use it as a way to
engage and inquiry together practice
good faith dialectic
and ultimately build communitas so i've
really been enjoying it and i look
forward to
seeing you here very soon awesome
uh and uh after i make some closing
announcements we'll just take a big
quick bio break and then we'll take
tyson in uh we have tons of events
tomorrow
uh tons meeting four one of them is
entrepreneurialism as a spiritual
practice with derek sivers
um he's the guy that i think created cd
baby he's a popular uh
entrepreneur that does blogging so
that's 7 p.m eastern time
that's going to be really fun talk and i
think it's what's
whatever october 22nd is um the first
series of high pitch
conversations in a new key so all the
the ladies of the store are going to
have a
really epic conversation benita roy nora
bateson right back
maria martinu and many more they're
gonna just
have a conversation then we'll have a
collective conversation uh so that's
gonna be very exciting
yeah it says 12 p.m on october 22nd you
can rcp
on the website uh we have a patreon and
uh you can sign up for the mailing list
so that being said
thank you everyone if you want to leave
right now you can leave right now if you
want to hang out a bit just check it out
you can do that as well so again thanks
for coming to stowa today